Under our law, corporations are the, you
know, have the rights of of individuals
in many respects, but they don't that
they don't have to meet the standards of
individuals. You know, they they they
get the they get the protection that
individuals get, but they can't go to
jail. You can't put a corporation in
jail, but you can put its leaders in
jail, but we don't. For the most part,
we don't.
Hi, I'm John Kuryaku and welcome back to
Deep Focus. Do you ever feel like the
economic deck is stacked against you?
You work hard, more than 40 hours a
week, and you just can't get ahead.
Inflation takes a bite. Medical
insurance is prohibitive. College costs
if you have kids are astronomical.
Well, maybe the deck actually is stacked
against you. Maybe that's the plan. And
what if you're a country and not a
person? You have some economic problems
for whatever reason, but then you go to
the likes of the the World Bank or the
International Monetary Fund or Wall
Street for help. You're humiliated and
essentially you're taken over. The
question then isn't is that the goal?
The question is why is that the goal?
Well, we're happy to be joined today by
one of the most articulate and respected
voices on international economic affairs
and banking who's out there. John
Perkins is a highly respected author and
commentator best known for his book
Confessions of an Economic Hitman in
which he describes playing a role in a
process of economic colonialization of
third world countries on behalf of what
he describes as a cabal of corporations,
banks, international financial
institutions, and the US government.
John, thanks so much for joining us.
I've been looking forward to this for a
long time.
>> It's my pleasure to be with you, John.
It's good to finally meet you, even if
from a if from a distance.
>> Mine.
>> I feel like we've known each other for a
long time already.
>> I wanted to start if we could with with
a big picture view. I spent a lot of
time at the CIA, including in countries
that were economic basket cases. They
all had one thing in common, massive
foreign debt, exactly the kind of debt
that you have warned about. Why is it
then that countries as diverse as
Argentina, Yemen, Greece, Pakistan, and
others keep going back to the World
Bank? They keep going back to the IMF or
to the US or to Wall Street when they
know what's going to happen to them. Why
do they do that?
>> Well, there's a number of reasons, but
perhaps the most obvious one is that
their leaders benefit from that. uh what
we might call corruption, but since it's
legal, it's legally not corruption. But
you know, the the people who run most of
these countries are connected to and are
their families own the big businesses in
these countries, the things like uh the
banks and the industries and and all the
merchant establishments, the big ones.
And uh so they benefit from these debts
because the debts are used to build
better highways, uh electrical systems,
uh airports and ports and and industrial
parks, things that really help them but
don't help most of the people out in the
might call the capo are the farmers, the
people. In fact, they they're hurt by
this because a lot of the interest
payments on the debt coming from things
that should go to social services. if
they come from funds that should be
paying for education, health care and
other social services. But the wealthy
and the powerful in these countries
really benefit and incidentally
they are also the ones who end up
working in high places in the World Bank
in the IMF. So it's their cronies
calling the shots there. So it's it
really is kind of this what we might
call it. I don't mean to sound sexist,
but the old boy network, you know, now
it's an old boy girl network. Uh, and so
it's it's it's it benefits them that
way. And in addition, they get some
other private perks like one of the
things we used to offer was, you know,
if you sign this loan, we'll make sure,
Mr. President, that you and your and
your family and all your friends and
their families, all your kids get get
into colleges in in in the United
States. Good colleges. We've got really
good connections. We're a Bostonbased
firm, the firm I worked for. We have
really good connections with MIT,
Harvard, Boston University, all these
amazing colleges. we'll get you in and
we'll give you full scholarships. And
that's worth a lot of money and it's
totally legal. In fact, we bragged about
it. You know, we we tell the Boston
Globe, "Hey, last year we gave $3
million to scholarships to people that
from from poor countries in Latin
America." Didn't bother to mention that
we gave the scholarships to the families
that really didn't need them.
And that's just one example of of of of
blatant corruption that is not
corruption because it's totally legal.
We were careful not to break any of the
laws around bribery and corruption, but
there were so many other ways to do it.
You wrote at length in uh Confessions of
an Economic Hitman about the nexus
between the firm where you worked and
NSA, the National Security Agency, and
you took a lot of heat for that,
including from people in the mainstream
media who said that that you had made it
up. In fact, though, when the New York
Times went back and investigated the
book, they found that you had indeed
told the truth.
So, we know that the likes of the CIA,
NSA, the FBI, and other three-letter
agencies u use international
organizations and banks as cover. Can
you tell us a little bit about that?
Tell us why NSA would be so interested
in having a foot in high level
international finance.
Well, all of these agencies are are
connected with what I like to call the
corportocracy,
uh, which is, you know, made up of
government officials and corporate
presidents and and you know, there's
this revolving door. So those people are
often one and the same that the people
Yeah. I often get a situation where
somebody in charge of of regulating the
oil industry
came right out of working for Texico or
or Chevron or somebody and and they're
going to go back into that industry when
they get out of government. So again,
it's part of this old boy network. And
so, you know, the NSA, the CIA, the the,
you know, all of these agencies uh are
so closely tied with this whole goal of
corportocratizing
the world, of making the world basically
a corporate empire. It's not exactly an
American empire, which is interesting
because if you take like Caliber and
recently moved to, you know, the Middle
East and and have their offices, we the
people of the United States don't
benefit from this for the most part.
There may be some benefits, but it's
really a corporate uh a corporate global
empire that's that's supported by the US
government in a very big way. Even to
the point of sending in troops if if an
oil company is threatened in in in
Colombia is what happened two years ago.
uh the United States will actually send
in troops or they call them advisers but
they really members of our military that
go in and and run things. Uh so so our
government supports this but the
American people
I don't benefit I mean you can make an
argument that when your when when your
country has the prominent language in
the world and the dollar is the
prominent currency when I go to other
countries I benefit from that. Yes. But
overall, I think we we suffer. And I
think we're seeing that today with a
huge backlash against us in favor of
China.
John, I remember sitting next to the
Greek ambassador to the United States at
an event back in 2008,
I guess it was at John's Hopkins
University. The Greek deputy prime
minister, who was also the finance
minister, was giving a presentation on
what was looking to be an economic
catastrophe in the making in Greece. I
turned to the ambassador and I said to
him, I don't see how you're going to get
out of this. And he said, "Neither do
I." So, what happened was what everybody
would have predicted. It was this
endless cycle of negotiations between
Greece and the World Bank and the IMF
and the European Central Bank. They
essentially took over the country. But
then word leaked out that Price
Waterhouse Coopers, the Greek
government's auditor, had been
falsifying economic records for years.
Um Goldman Sachs was involved in the
falsification of those records. But in
the end, nobody from PWC or from Goldman
Sachs or for that matter,
you know, the Greek government was ever
prosecuted and the Greeks are now
indebted for generations to come to
these powerful Western uh entities. What
should have been done or or could things
have been done differently?
Well, I I think Greece really became the
fall boy for uh the catastrophe, the
financial catastrophe that swept through
Europe and much of the world back in
those back in back in the 2008, 2007,
2008 at that time. And you know, I have
to say, I mean, I to a certain degree
that the the the Greek government has to
take responsibility because there was a
lot of corruption. But you've always got
to ask yourself, who does the
corruption? Who does the corrupt? I
mean, we talk about corruption in
Greece. We talk about corruption in
Latin American countries and African
countries, but you got to ask yourself,
who's doing the corruption? I was one of
those people. And I don't know whether
you with the CIA got involved in that at
all, but I mean, that was part of my job
was, as I've mentioned before, legal
corruption and and and it can be done
illegally, too. But who who's doing the
corruption and and for what reason? Uh
but you know I I I think you you also
hit upon a very important point which is
the individuals involved whether it's in
Greece or anywhere else in the world
don't get taken down. The companies may
get fined. The companies may may or may
not admit to guilt. Sometimes they don't
admit to guilt. Sometimes they do. They
get fined. They they they struck a deal.
But nobody goes to prison. Nobody gets
slapped on the wrist even uh because
they're protected by the corporations.
And you know under our law corporations
are have the you know have the rights of
of individuals in many respects but they
don't that they don't have to meet the
standards of individuals. You know they
they they get the they get the
protection that individuals get but they
can't go to jail. You can't put a
corporation in jail but you can put its
leaders in jail but we don't for the
most part.
>> That's exactly right. You know, in
Greece, I served in Greece from 1998 to
2000 and and I travel back to Greece
regularly all the time. Uh they had a
defense minister by the name of Akis
Tohadopulos.
This guy was the definition of
corruption. I remember um I remember
reading in the paper that he had bought
a new house and it was directly across
the street from the Parthonon. And I I
knew what those houses went for, right?
I read the real estate section of the
Greek papers. This guy makes $80,000 a
year and he buys a $6 million house. And
then he's hosting parties. It's nicer
than the prime minister's mansion. And
so finally, finally, his corruption was
so bad that they they did something
about it. And they found that he had
taken millions of dollars in bribes from
Seammens, the German company, to um to
throw it was a submarine contract their
way. And he was arrested, his wife was
arrested, his daughter was arrested, his
son-in-law. They had been spreading the
wealth. Yeah.
>> And he's sentenced to life without
parole. Okay. Then they let him out two
years later and they said, "Oh, he's an
old man. He served his country for all
those years honorably. He made a
mistake."
Well, okay. What about the $6 million
house that he bought? Well, where's what
are we going to put him in the street?
He can he can keep the house. All right.
So, two years later, they're all out of
prison. He's still in the giant house.
And it's like, h, you know, everybody
forgot about it or forgave it or and for
the for the Greeks, like the the man on
the street, Greeks, they would just
shake their heads and say, well, that's
that's Greece.
>> Does that remind you at all, John, of
what's been going on in this country in
the last few months with
>> isn't that the tr the truth?
>> January, January 6, etc., etc., etc. I
mean, think about it.
>> Yeah.
>> And I want I'd like to ask you, so can
can you talk at all about what were you
doing in Greece? Were you involved in
these kinds of deals? Were you bribing
people?
>> Thank God. Uh I would be so ashamed if I
had to tell you yes. I was in uh
counterterrorism operations. So my job
was was to work with the Greek uh
intelligence service and the Greek
police to disrupt. At first it was Arab
uh it was Abuidal and the Libyans and
the PFLP and the DFLP. Um and then it
became very specific to the Greek groups
revolutionary organization 17 November
popular revolutionary struggle. So we're
we're jetting around Europe interviewing
old men who used to be in the red
brigades and axion direct and B minehoff
gang and you remember those those groups
from the 70s. They were all old men by
the time I got involved. But no, if I
had something to do with economics, I
would be so ashamed of myself today.
What about uh Okay, I I'm not going to
go there. Forget it. But isn't Greece
one of those places where the where the
where the CIA has some black black holes
and some some some some places where
they interrogate people that they
wouldn't
>> Oh. Oh my god. Thank God for that too.
Another thing I would have been So I've
become a Greek citizen, I should add.
>> Oh, excellent. So you you speak Greece.
>> Oh yeah, I speak Greek. I got my
citizenship. My kids all have Greek
citizenship.
>> You're so lucky.
You know what? To tell you the honest to
God's truth, I I had it in the back of
my mind that if I needed to bolt one
day,
>> I ought to have the proper paperwork to
do it.
>> Yeah. I was in I was in Greece last uh
about about two years ago and just I
love Greece. I I spent time there when I
was an economic hitman, too. Uh, we went
went to bunch of the islands and and and
and you can't beat the history and the
>> you can't beat it. I wanted to tell you
too, I was in Argentina.
>> I'm going to say I was in Argentina 22
or 23 years ago,
you had warned
about the likes of Elliot Associates,
one of the big hedge funds based in New
York. And the reason I bring up
Argentina is that Elliot bought
millions, maybe billions of dollars in
Argentine government bonds, which were
essentially junk bonds, and Elliot
demanded repayment, and it literally
pushed Argentina into bankruptcy. So I
wanted to ask you on a broader level
what what's the role of hedge funds in
some of these terrible economic stories
the these terrible stories about the the
loss of economic sovereignty and should
individual banks and investment houses
have that kind of power and authority
over a country
I don't think they should but the
question is what do we do about it you
know the idea of the vulture funds that
you know this whole huge business in
that of going into countries like
Argentina and many others and buying up
these securities or other forms of debt
that that that have basically downgraded
to nothing to zero essentially and and
then and then demanding that the country
repay them. And it's a you know it's
another it's a crime. It's a it's you
know it's just it's a crime. that it how
do you how do you prevent these things
when you've got these massive
governmental institutions on in both
countries the United States and
Argentina backing them and and and going
along with it and playing a role in it
probably what Argentine politicians were
benefiting from this we don't know but I
suspect there were a few that were doing
that
Argentina is such a prime example of an
incredibly amazing country with
incredible things
>> wonderful resources and culture and and
and great restaurants,
>> great amazing worldclass restaurants. I
that was the first time I had been to
Argentina and I remember even on the
first day just looking around and
saying, "Wow, I could live here."
>> And then you learn what a corrupt
economic basket case it is.
>> Oh.
>> And then you have to ask yourself, how
do these poor people survive?
>> Yeah.
>> It's just Yeah, that's a And and yet
they survive. They they they look they
look great, you know? They're very
fashionable and uh I remember being
there in the in the in the 70s when the
in the military gentto was and I was
there with the US uh major general uh
who was a senior vice president in my
company Charles T. Maine and and we were
there together because Maine was in
deeply involved in the uh design and and
construction of a huge hydroelectric
project that connected that was on the
on the Parano River between between
Orway and and and Argentina. And you
know there were these roadblocks all
over the place. You you drive along, you
know, these guys would jump out at you
from with a roadblock with with these
automatic weapons pointed at you. and
and I felt I was fortunate to be there
with the US Army general frankly and you
know he had all of his credentials and
he was he was retired but uh they they
respected that and we were working with
the uh with the Genta in a in an
indirect manner through the
Interamerican Development Bank and the
World Bank and the IMF who were all
involved as was the US government
supporting that terrible government and
we were doing something similar in Chile
and throughout Latin America. and and a
lot of the rest of the world. It was it
was just it was outrageous when you come
right down to it. And that that that
sent Argentina into a tail spin. It
already had gone through the whole
perone. It had it's been going through
problems for a long time, but I think it
that was a that that that decade of the
70s was such a monumental moment in in
the history of Argentina and so much of
Latin America. and the Argentines were,
you know, were deeply
connected. There were a lot of rumors,
which I can't prove, that that the CIA
would would call on their counterparts
in Argentina to do that dirty work in
Latin America. So, the CIA didn't
actually do it. That's more that's one
of the allegations around the the the
the alleged assassination of of Omar
Trios of Panama that it was actually
done by the Argentines. None none of
this can be proven, but uh there's
enough people feeling that way that you
got to suspect there's some truth around
around it someplace. And you probably
know more about that than I do. I I I
believe those stories to tell you the
truth. Um because I know how the CIA
operates and uh you know, one of the
things they taught us in training and we
we came to see it kind of as a bad joke
was always let others do your dirty
work.
always. So you have at least plausible
deniability.
Why would you want to kill Omar Dio
um
when you can get the Argentines to do
it,
>> right?
>> Why why why would you want to go after
Chilean leftists when you can put Pinoch
in power and have him do it,
>> right?
>> It it's sick.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's a it's a fact of life.
>> Well, it's a story of empire. Yes, it
is. That's exactly what it is.
>> And done throughout history. And and I
think this gets us to I'm often asked,
so what's the big problem? Yeah. I talk
about how we have a death economy, an
economic system that's consuming and
polluting itself into extinction. We
have the opportunity right now to move
into a life economy, an economy that
used solar and wind and you know,
regenerates
destroyed environments, plants, trees,
and so on and so forth. And people ask
me, so what's the biggest thing holding
us back? And my answer is is leadership.
Uh that the the world's leaders don't
don't want that. And we're seeing that
very clearly in the United States today,
but we're also seeing it in Russia and
in China and and and in Argentina with
Malay. I mean, he's he's in that same
category. Uh so so it's it's I I think
that's that's in throughout history you
look at leadership is always
the controlling factor and at at the
early stage of the United States I think
it you know was it's a very mixed bag
because my dad used to say and my dad
was a fairly conservative Republican but
he used to say you know the American
Revolution just replaced the monarchy
with a with an oligarchy in the United
States and George Washington was part of
that. But Washington also I think was a
very very a guy with great integrity and
you know he he denied serving a third
term. They they really wanted him to
because they said no no no I want to set
a precedent. The president should not be
president for more than two terms. I I
think we were lucky to have that kind of
leadership at the beginning despite its
falls. Uh but uh things have gone down
downhill
>> very much so. Um, c could you have even
imagined 20 years ago that there would
be an American worth $444 billion? How
does an individual in a lifetime
accumulate $444 billion of wealth other
than by stealing it or making it on the
backs of all other Americans?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I I understand Jeff
Bezos had this great idea to sell books
online, but is Jeff Bezos really worth a
$400 billion?
You know, Elon Musk uh signed a new
contract what a couple of weeks ago in
which he got a $46 billion signing
bonus. What's that? And here we are 50
years
after
these economic problems uh cropped up.
as an example, in Argentina or in Chile
or in Brazil even. And 50 years later,
they're struggling with exactly the same
problems. And on top of those problems,
just like we have here in the United
States, much of the wealth is
concentrated in the hands of of
individuals.
Few individuals. Yeah. But you know the
other thing, John, I think it's
important and and you you with your
history with the CIA to to really look
at how uh how the United States is
playing into the hands of China now. So
So this we all this the things we're
talking about were done to create an
empire that was supported by the United
States and and the big all these big
corporations. And you and I both were
involved in this process. a lot of
people were a lot of money was spent on
this from that after World War II
especially after World War II going on
through through all these decades and
yet today it's all being torn down and
you know China's been on the on the rise
anyway but uh we we've been we made a
lot of mistakes before uh this
particular time in history we you know
we we we devoted so many resources to
Iraq and and Afghanistan
Well, uh, we we it pretty much ignored
Africa and Latin America. China moved
into America, Latin America and and
Africa
>> didn't successfully.
>> But yeah, but now in the in most recent
times, I mean, to to impose 50% tariffs
on on India, where do you think India's
got to turn to?
>> Exactly.
>> The Indians have robust trade relations
with both China and Russia.
>> Yeah. if they if they can't sell their
goods to the United States because of
50% tariffs, no problem. They'll just go
to their new markets.
>> Right. Right. So, you know, we're so
playing into the hands of of of China,
it's a um
well, we'll have to see where this is
all taking us. and and and from from
from a real human perspective, the
biggest problem is that all of us,
whether we're in China or the United
States or Russia, are ignoring the real
existential threat to humanity, which
is, you know, a an economic system
that's destroying us. It's causing
climate change. Climate change is a
problem, but it's not the problem. It's
a symptom of a much bigger problem which
is this which is a system that's based
on maximizing short-term materialistic
consumption and for corporations
short-term profits and the corporations
ought to run the world basically on this
with this goal of maximizing short-term
profits regardless of the social and
environmental costs. So we've we've so
that's the that's the bigger problem and
the Chinese buy into that same sort of
scenario. the Russians do. Uh we do
basically everybody does. And that that
to me is the the shame of what what's
happening now is that we're all being so
distracted
uh from that real existential problem by
these created problems of of of
antagonism between countries. Like come
on,
>> we're all living on this planet. You
know,
>> it's right the planet. a vested interest
in success.
>> Yeah,
>> the plasma doesn't see the borders. You
know, we know that from the pictures we
take from satellites. I mean, if you go
to Google maps, you'll see the borders,
but if you go to really a bigger picture
of the world, there are no borders.
>> That's right.
That's right, John. Let's say a country
like Portugal or Ireland or Tunisia
has a great deal of economic
instability, right? They've got a
refugee crisis. Energy prices are high.
They need to get back on track. So, they
turn to John Perkins for advice. What
kind of advice would you give? Presuming
that the advice wouldn't be to, you
know, make an appointment with the World
Bank, the IMF, and and Wall Street. What
would you tell them?
>> So, so, so what are they looking for
from me? Advice is to do as to what do
>> their economy is is suffering because
they've got high debt,
>> right?
>> Okay.
>> Manufacturing is off. They have a
refugee crisis. Pretty much what we're
seeing all over southern Europe and
Northern Africa.
>> Yeah.
>> What What would you tell them to do?
>> Yeah. I think first of all, it's it's to
form alliances with other countries that
are in in similar dire straits and and
and
actually leveraged this this uh
competition between China and the United
States to get much better financial
conditions, loans, better terms and
conditions for for loans. They need
money in order to develop these things.
They need markets and but if they can
come together I recently was on a
program out of Africa and was asked that
same question. Uh I mean what what what
about what would what what what advice
uh should I give the the Kenyans and um
you know it's like join get get every
get all get all the African countries
together you've got you've got more
resources anywhere you're you're the
richest continent in the world from a
resource standpoint and the poorest
from from an economic standpoint but
you've also got the youngest population
in the world. I think the the the the
average population that the age of the
average population right now is 19, you
know, and and and China recognizes that
and China's getting older older people.
They they want they want to involve
Africa more because they know they're
going to need the young people to to
subsidize the older people of China. So
get these get together on this and and
stand up form alliances and you know I
think that's the only way this is going
to work is if if these countries in
Latin America and Africa there's a long
history that makes that very difficult
for them to do. I understand it's it's
got huge obstacles, but that would be my
advice that you've got to do that and
then get the money to come in and make
sure you get value added that if you've
got all these mineral resources uh in
Africa, you've got incredible amounts of
things, lithium right now, which is such
a huge thing, and and cobalt and and and
other things, and make sure that you get
money to build the industries there to
process these materials and make the
products from them, the batteries,
whatever it
you know, so get the value at it. And
the only way you're going to really make
that happen is if you guys unite and
stand up to the world and incidentally,
China recognizes that. And that's where
the bricks bank comes in.
>> You took the words right out of my
mouth? I was going to ask you, is bricks
the start of a solution?
>> Well, bricks appears to many people in
those countries as as as allowing them
to move in that direction, you've got a
big major
uh power player in the world, China,
that can help direct you in this this in
this direction. But you know, the
problem of course is that that China's
goals are very probably very similar to
the United States, and that's to build
their own empire and have control over
these things. So, you know, it's it it
it it it maybe lights the way in that
you need to unite. Uh I don't think it's
quite as important. the brick stands for
Brazil, Russia, India, South Africa and
China. Uh, China and South Africa. You
know, maybe that's a little bit too
diverse. You know what what I think that
the African countries could form their
own union and the Latin American
countries their union and then you could
stand up to both China and the United
States and you could leverage you know
like oh we're going to go to China you
know ch China is only going to require a
2% interest rate and the United States
is requiring 7% or you know something
and so then you get this competition but
um United you know United stance. It's
one of the reasons that the United
States has been so successful is that we
did we have been united on many many
policies ever since the civil war.
And isn't it interesting that Moamar
Akadafi
who would have agreed with everything
you just said and actually was promoting
African unity, he had turned away from
the Arab League and was promoting
African unity was taken out by the West.
It's symbolic, isn't it? It's a miracle.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Let's not forget that he was
threatening to use the gold diner uh as
the currency for buying oil.
>> That's exactly right.
>> You don't you don't survive an attack on
the US dollar.
>> No. And that's
>> he he he didn't. Saddam Hussein didn't
and others haven't.
>> That's right.
>> John, what are the major economic
mistakes that countries are making today
in their economies? Is it is it a
failure to diversify? Is it taking on
too much debt? And how can countries
begin to protect themselves?
>> Well, again, your your diversification
question is a is an important one
because uh again, if you go to China
with its idea of the new Silk Road, the
Belgian and road initiative, uh it is
saying to the world, look, you don't
need to diversify. uh do whatever you do
best. Use the resources that you have
and we will help you uh get the value
added from them by cooperating with
other countries around the world. We'll
help you build roads and railroads and
ports and airports that help you trade
with everybody. And they'll say, you
know, well, the United States, if if you
get a most most favored nation clause
with the United States, let's say you're
Ecuador, you have a most favored nation
clause, and the United States says, "Oh,
you know, we will, you know, we you'll
have a great trading agreement with
you." China goes in and says, "No, you
don't need to trade with us. We're going
to help you build a new port and
airports and roads so that you can trade
with Argentina and with with uh with
South Africa and with India and all over
the world. we're going to help you
expand all of this so you can really
focus on on the resources that you have
best. And so, you know, this whole this
whole idea of of of how do we how do we
maximize trade? How do we maximize
resources? Again, you can go to the
United States, you know, we don't we
don't try to get every state to be
self-sufficient. Uh, you know, we say uh
if one state has a lot of oil, let them
produce more oil. And if another state
is producing
whatever eggs, let them let them sell
eggs to the people producing the oil and
and and so on. I mean, we've been we've
been very strategic in this country
about that between the states. But
that's that model works for the world
also.
>> That's a good point.
>> And China recognizes that again. China's
using that. China's economic hitmen have
just done a bangup job. you know,
they've been so so efficient. I I found
a great map here if I can find it. There
it is. Uh that shows so this is two this
is the year 2000. The United States was
a number one trading partner with 80% of
the world's countries. And this is the
world 2020.
China now is the number one trading
partner with 80% of the world's
countries. And it's gotten it's gotten
more that that's gone even more toward
China in the last five years. This is
the oldest. This is the most recent one
I have. But in the last 5 years, China
has moved into some of these countries
like these like Colombia, like the blue
ones over here. Uh so I mean that's so
telling that was that was in 20 years.
20 years.
>> Yeah. And how did that happen? Because
China's economic hitmen are damn good at
their job. You know, I taught at an MBA
program in Shanghai a few years back,
and I realized as soon as I got there
that why I was there was because they
wanted to pick my brain about what
mistakes I had made and the successes
I've had and how to maximize the
successes and minimize the mistakes,
you know, and they've done that.
>> But China seems like an exemplar. Are
are there any other countries out there
that are that are doing it right?
Well, I'm not sure I would say China is
doing it right, but what they are doing
if I mean if you want to say becoming an
empire is doing it right, they are doing
that right for sure. And of course they
they did have 10% roughly 10% economic
growth every year for 30 years. They
brought 900 million people out of dire
poverty. Nobody else in the world has
ever done anything like that. So yeah,
they had a pretty successful model. And
um that also is an incredible selling
point for their economic hitman. You go
to Argentina, you go to any country in
the world and you say, "Hey, look at our
model. Look at the success we've had."
In the meantime, look at the United
States. Your your your federal minimum
wage rate hasn't increased since 1973.
It's the minimum wage is the same today
as it was in 1973 or 74. Do you want
that model? You know, and what kind of
economic growth is the United States
had? Nothing compared to us. So, you
know, these are all perceptions, but
reality is molded by perception. And the
Chinese are extremely good at at selling
the perception of what they do so well
and what the United States does so
poorly. And we've we've played right
into their hands, John. Right into their
hands.
>> I think you're right.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. John, uh, I wanted to, uh, wrap up
by asking your thoughts on the US
economy, good, bad, or indifferent. The
data seem to be pulling us in different
directions at the same time. And does it
matter that we're almost entirely a
service economy now?
Wow. I wish I had a a crystal ball to
see where that's going to take us. uh
but um I don't think it's a bad thing to
be a service economy as long as the
world is structured in a way where where
international trade uh serves us. But as
we move the tariffs are doing the
opposite of that. So they're putting us
in a in a very difficult position where
we can't afford to import the things
that we don't produce here, which is an
awful lot, you know, because we're not
we're not producing these things. We're
not manufacturing them. And will this
stimulate manufacturing in the United
States as as the administration says it
will? I don't know. It might, but it's
really hard to believe that that most
Americans while we're closing out the
the the immigrants uh that that mo most
Americans really want to work in heavy
industry. Uh you know, how many how many
friends did you have at college that
that wanted to go and shovel coal? Uh
so it's hard for me to see how that's
going to work. So I think being a
service economy and and a a
technological economy, one that's one
that can sell us technology around the
world could really serve our purposes.
But it makes it very difficult to do
that if you've got the kind of economic
system that's that's being globalized
today where it's going to become
increasingly expensive for us to buy
things that we absolutely need from
other countries and to produce them here
at home. I just I I don't know how that
could it become. Mhm.
>> Yeah.
>> Unless robotics come in to take place
that the place of that, but
>> which would make it worse even.
>> It could make it worse. Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> John Perkins, thank you so much for
being with us. John Perkins is the
author of several books, but most
famously, Confessions of an Economic
Hitman. Don't miss it. It's been out for
a long time and it's still in print.
Yes.
>> Yeah. There's a third ed So, it's a
trilogy. So there's a third edition
which focuses on the econ on China's
economic hitman strategy.
>> Fantastic.
>> And that's in audio and and print or
whatever you want. And John, I would
just like to end by by saying to your
audience, this has been we've talked
about a lot of negative things, but I
think we should all feel blessed to be
alive at this time because we are at a
cusp in human evolution. You know, we
are at a time when we are really going
to define what this world looks like for
our children and grandchildren and great
grandchildren. It's a huge opportunity
and the fact we're exposing the bad
sides of what we does is it's important.
It's important to be self-critical, but
it's also important to look to the
future and see that we can turn this
around. I think you know everybody who's
listening to to your program and who's
alive now uh should feel blessed to be
alive at this time and to be able to
participate in this. I do. I feel very
blessed to have this opportunity.
>> I agree with you. I do as well. Thanks
again for being with us.
>> My pleasure, John. Thanks for all you
do.
>> Thank you.